New insurance company,
my lord. Um in in this matter I peer for
the revenue with my learn friends Mr.
Baldry, Professor Burroughs and Miss
Bulbrano and the test claimants are
represented by Mr. Mr. Beasley and Mr.
Brenda who I believe are all going to um
address your your lordships later on or
tomorrow.
Um
to begin with my lord this is you will
have seen the latest installment in a
saga which has been running in a in a
number of gripification orders and and
other um related cases for quite a
number of years. Um these claims were
first made in 2003
um as were the original claims in FII.
Um and as you will see, you understand
we began in 2003 with pretty much a
clean slate. Um nobody knew what
European law was going to be or indeed
um some aspects of the law of uh the
domestic law of restitution etc. Uh
we've now come quite a long way. Um
I was proposing to to um structure my
submissions in the following way. Uh I
was going to begin with some
introductory comments which I hope will
put everything in context and may remind
you lordships of some matters which I'm
sure you would have in mind in any event
and then I was going to take you to the
the statutory provisions in particular
the provisions about act um which we
have to look at that that won't take too
long and and then I was proposing to
trace
um to some extent the background o of
the various decisions and and to explain
and put them in context in particular
leading up to the second reference in
FII which is obviously an important
decision in relation to issue one. Um
and then what I was proposing to do was
to deal with issue one and the cross
appeal which is issue four
uh and and then to deal with issue five
which is also a cross appeal. The reason
I'm dealing with them in that order is
because I think logically they go they
all go together. They're all part of the
process as I will explain hopefully of
of determining
um both what what was lawful and
unlawful under European law uh and what
what is taken to have happened in the
past.
Um and then I will deal with issue two
which is the issue about compound
interest and finally issue three which
is the issue which we require permission
and is there a can just define issue
five because the respondents relate it
to issue three. Yes. Uh whereas you
separated
Yes. Issue five I I I would submit is an
issue
where you best find it to define well
there there is a statement of facts and
issues that perhaps
the these were these were issues that
were um determined by the code of
appeal. Yes. It doesn't really identify
issue five does it? It it does over the
page it says the following issues arise
where a there's a and b
and and and and
what both of those issues are aimed at
is to determine where there was an
undifferiated pool of act which was both
lawful and unlawful.
You require a method of determining
whether it was lawful or unlawful act
which mean something happened to is it
prat or first so to speak lawful against
lawful oral against law unlawful. Yes.
Exactly. Yes. But but what it is my lord
I'm going to come back to this when I in
my introductory remarks. What it is is
part of the process of determining in
essence what the facts were or what the
facts are treated to have been at the
time because at the time when all this
happened nobody of course was aware that
there was unlawful and lawful act
was a single amorphous mass and the UK
legislation dealt with it as a single
mass because there was no reason to
differentiate it but but when you come
to these claims it is necessary in a
number of cases and I'll take you others
to to decide
when you had a pool of ACT which was
both lawful and unlawfully charged
whether it was a lawful ACT or the
unlawful ACT which was for instance set
off against corporation tax because that
makes a can make a big difference to the
to the claims. So there has to be a way
of determining that because there is a
different treatment depending on whether
it's lawful or unlawful act. So the and
I I I I I'll take you to some what Mr.
Justice Henderson said about this
because he explained uh in a couple of
paragraphs um this this process A2
that's what issue 5 is about we it's
basically A and B is it A and B yes
there was a third issue in the court of
appeal but there's been no appeal
against that that decision so it's it's
only only two of the three issues that
were dealt with by the court of appeal
and and the revenues position in all of
these um and you'll see the same comes
when we look at um FI and other other
contexts is that it should be dealt with
on a prata basis. There's no there's no
other sensible basis to to deal with it.
Um so can I begin then by a few remarks.
Um the first is maybe obvious but it's
important to keep in mind that the trial
from which this is an appeal only
concerned the test claimant's claims in
unjust enrichment uh for restitution.
It has claims for damages, but it was
agreed before the trial that those would
not be dealt with at that trial. So,
they they're standing over. Can I just
ask, is there going to be a transcript
of of this hearing or not? I understood
there was going to be, but I don't I
don't see anyone. Well, I think fine.
No, no. So, it just Well, it's helpful
to know. It just affects the detail of
the note. You I understand my body. Yes.
Right. So, no transcript. Thank you. No,
I'm not suggesting they should be.
Right. There are there are some
computers with nobody behind them.
There may be a transcript. We're used to
working without it, but um it's quite
useful to know, right?
Um so the claims to actually watch it.
You can watch it rather um yes patiently
on the screen afterwards and transcribe
that. Yes.
Uh so this was a trial in relation to
only the claims on just enrichment. Um
the damages claims have been stood over.
Uh of course the damages claims have
have two problems from the test
claimment's point of view. One is a
limitation period which is only six
years. Um and I'll I'll come back to why
that's quite important. and the and the
other is uh they have to show that there
was a sufficiently serious breach of
European law before they can yes mount
claims for damages.
In the FI litigation, this issue was
argued out
uh before Mr. Justice Henderson and the
Court of Appeal
and their decisions in both cases was
that there was no there was not a
sufficiently serious breach and so there
couldn't be claims for damages. These
are Frankovich claims. Frankovich claims
me. Exactly. Um
that is one of the issues where the a
permission application is pending before
this court.
And again I'll come back to that.
But it is important to keep this in
mind. These are not damages claims. And
and you may have seen Mr. Justice
Henderson's deciding in a few occasions
that the claims the claimants were
planning to make actually sounded in
damages rather than in restitution and
therefore he dismissed the claims uh as
restitutionary claim. Well, on compound
interest um and he he said that, didn't
he? Didn't am I wrong? He said it in
relation to a claim in relation to
section 242 for instance. That's one
example. Anyway, there's a p I would
certainly ball the passage. Yeah,
because the the argument was this is a
dam a damages claim the revenue said not
truly a restitutionary claim and he up
upheld he he he he said it actually in
relation to I think setting off act
lawful act against unlawful corporation
tax didn't it but be that as it may come
to we'll come back to that one yes um
the second point is that the the test
claimment uh credential has an open has
open accounting periods from 1994
in other words, their their returns are
subject to inquiry still from that from
that year.
And this means that the
the corporation tax claims
can be dealt with under the statutory
procedure for for those years
and that and that's why at the end of
the decision you may have seen Mr.
Justice Henderson discussing auto a case
called autologic which was a decision of
the House of Lords
which said that if you can bring a
statutory claim to recover tax even tax
unlawfully charged under EU law then you
should do that rather than bringing a
high court claim for for restitution or
damages.
So all the corporation tax claims from
are currently stayed. They haven't been
dealt with in these proceedings.
What what has been dealt with are the
pre94 corporation tax claims
and the claims in relation to ACT
for all years up until 1999,
arguably 1998 when ACT was abolished.
This is one of the reasons why mistake
claims are important in this case
because it's necessary to bring claims
of mistake to take take you back to 20
to to before 1994. In fact, to take the
take back before 199, the claims were
brought in 2003, a six-year period would
would go back to 2000 1997. But before
that it's necessary to bring claims in
mistake.
And just for completeness the
corporation tax position was was
equalized in 2009.
So there was there was no longer any
breach of EU law after that. All
virtually all foreign dividends were
exempted from UK tax.
The third point my lord is that
credential you'll be aware is a test
claimment
for all of the other members of the CFC
and dividend GLLO
and of of course credential is entitled
to whatever judgment it's entitled to
and to whatever claims it can it can it
can um validate
but you can you can separate in my
submission the resolution of credentials
claims from the resolution of this
common issues of law which arise in the
GLLO uh and it's important certainly
from the point of view of the revenue
and I imagine too from the point of view
of the test claimants and the other
claimants who are I would understand
funding this litigation
that you resolve the issues
correctly as a matter of principle
In other words, it's not sufficient to
say well it doesn't really matter in
credential's case but when we come to
look at for instance compound interest
you logistics will have seen that the
the result for credential is very
similar whether it's section 35A
interest or compound interest
but that's not necessarily the case for
all of the for all the other um
claimments in the GLO and that's why we
we would wish to have these decisions
these um issues decided by this court as
a matter of principle.
So
the next my next point the fourth point
is is is how these cases work. What is
the shape of the the litigation?
And I would submit you you can you can
divide it up conveniently into four
sections.
The first is the fundamental questions.
What is the breach of EU law
and what is and what therefore is the
appropriate conforming interpretation or
disapplication of UK law. in the light
of that
and of course that that's where the
various references to the European code
of just code of justice of the European
Union have come in
and and that's and that's the issue to
which issues one and issue four the
cross appeal relayed
the the second aspect of these cases is
to determine what are the facts
of a particular case. Now the facts
obviously include things like where when
dividends were paid and from where
when tax was paid
but but it also includes facts which
have to be determined in in retrospect
and this is going back to the point I
was making earlier. There has to be a
determination
of matters which simply didn't exist at
the time.
You have to determine
how mixed funds
which as far as everyone's concerned at
the time and as far as the law was
concerned where we're were a single fund
how they are to be treated.
If I can take an example,
your lordships will be aware that ACT
could be set off against mainstream
corporation tax.
So you pay ACT, the company pays it in
respect to a dividend and then when it
comes to pay mainstream corporation tax,
it can set off the ACT, it is paid.
However,
um ACT wasn't necessarily set off in the
year in which it was paid. quite often
act would be carried forward and and and
set off later.
Um,
it is necessary
in order to determine the correct
amounts of restitution in these cases to
determine when particular amounts of ACT
were set off
because the because the ACT that was set
off would would almost inevitably
include both lawful and unlawfully
charged ACT.
So that that is that's an example of a
situation that you have to determine.
There are there are numerous other
examples in in the FI case things were
even more complicated because ACT could
be surrendered to other group companies
and and that happened of course in
relation to to BAT which is a test
claimment in FII. So it was necessary
then to decide what act had been
surrendered and then and then when that
was utilized by the by the subsidiary
company for instance. So this is all
part I would submit of determining what
the facts were or what they were what
they are to be treated to have been for
the purposes of this litigation
and and as I said earlier issue five is
an aspect of that part. What once you've
decided what the facts were,
unlawful tax was was charged, some tax
was paid, some tax was set off, it's
then a question of applying the the
rules, the the English domestic law of
unjust enrichment to those facts in
order to determine what claims can be
made. And and of course if we ever come
to the question of damages you would
have to apply the the rules of damages
causation remoteness etc to determine
what loss has been suffered as a result
of of these facts. Um
and and issues two and three
uh concern that question. How do the
rules how do the the rules of unjust
enrichment? What is the what is the
domestic law of unjust enrichment and
how does it apply to these
circumstances?
The the final step in the process is is
um I say mechanical. I don't wish to um
in any way downplay the complexities and
difficulties of it but it it involves
calculations.
There have to be many many calculations
done afterwards applying these
principles to decide what the answer is
in pounds and pence at the end of the
day.
So that there are computations that have
to be done and there are spreadsheets
etc.
and they apply the principles that I've
been discussing the first three but the
principles that I've set out are not
computational principles. These are all
legal principles.
uh they're decided by courts.
So it's not right as I think the test
claimments suggest to say that some of
these are the principles I've been
discussing in one to three are actually
purely computational principles.
They're not
I would like next to to take your
lordship just briefly to to the
pleadings just to show you where the
what this case looked like when it
started.
Um
these are in the the second what what's
appendix
being told what it looked like when it
started. Well, um there is a purpose
that a a number of times in the um case
the test claimants say such and such a
point wasn't pleaded and and I just
wanted to show you how things stood as
regards the pleadings. I mean the court
of appeal were very critical of the
pleadings. They were my lord. Yes. And I
think rightly were all things to all men
more or less. Yes. Aren't we ultimately
going to be just as interested if not
more in um how the matter was argued?
What points were actually I was going to
raised below because one of the
objections to one of your heads of issue
is um that um it wasn't raised below.
Yes, that's issue three in particular.
Uh right. Yes. Well, yes. What I was
going to show you, my lord, first
briefly was the pleadings and then I
what I was going to show you was the the
skeletons for the for the trial which
are essentially will essentially be as
you will see show you what the issues
were at that stage. What? At a high
level of abstraction apparently at a
high level. Okay. Yes. Anyway, you can
see well let's look at but
the other way of dealing with it might
be to relate the pleadings to particular
issue when you um yes come to it but
want to do it now. That may be a
problem. Basically I I I think I think
what I was really going to show you was
that you don't really get any help at
all from the pleadings on the issues
that we're we're dealing with. Um it's
tab 20 provides the answer to my
question.
Yes.
Yes. Why we Well, the reason we're
looking at them a lot is because it
answers it answers a point that's being
made by the test claimments. Okay.
Um it's tab 20 MS 3914.
[Music]
These these are the pleadings that as
they stood second amended particulars of
claim at the time of the trial.
Uh these are the particulars of claim.
Um and and these were drafted
before
the second reference in FII
and they weren't amended after that. So
that there is no you won't find any
mention in these pleadings
of a claim based on the foreign nominal
raid.
I think it's right to say the basis of
these pleadings
was that
foreign dividends, certainly EU
dividends, possibly non-EU dividends
after 1993 should be treated as exempt
from UK tax
and and that we we will see when we look
at the skeleton that continued to be the
test claimant's primary case up until
trial.
So yeah, there's there's there's nothing
in these pleadings about the foreign
nominal rate or why it applies or how
how it applies which which rate of tax
you apply. They pursued exemption rather
than um credit. They're ping exemption
because to be fair before 2011 before
the second reference nobody had thought
of foreign nominal rates as being
relevant to any of this. So they're
pursuing exemption. Yes. And and as
regards interest,
um all that you will find, I think, is
is page
um MS 3926,
which is right at the end,
the bottom of page 350 of the bundle.
um which is a a claim in the prayer
for for interest.
Now I I think to be fair we we ought to
also just look at the the document prior
to that which is tab 19 which is the
claim form because the the details of
brief details of claim are slightly
different in relation to interest.
It's paragraph six. It's on page MS3913.
So they do mention
the rules of law and or equity
whereas in the particular claim it only
mentions the rules of equity.
But what is quite clear is that there is
no there is no um detailed pleading
of a claim in unjust enrichment in
relation to time value
period periods
and
we'll come back to that when we come to
the issue as to what exactly the
elements of that claim should be.
But that that that is entirely what the
pleadings say.
the the trial was conducted on the basis
of I think as a court of appeal recorded
a an agreed set of issues and and what
was said in the skeletons prior to the
trial
and the claimment skeleton there is a
respondent's bundle
um
volume E.
This is this is the bundle that um we
got a few days ago. Is it? Yes, I think
that's it. Yes, it's tab four of that
bundle
and you can see it begin the the this
issue begins on MS it begins on MS 4224
but that that only has the the issue set
out and then 4225
paragraph 52 the claimant submit
primarily that the provisions imposing
the D5 charge and foreign source
dividend should be disapplied in
circumstances where it's unlawful
alternatively in the alternative the
claimments submit the prison should be
construed as granting a credit for
underlying tax at the nominal corporate
tax rate of the member state or or third
country which the company paying the
dividends established. You saying that
this is the first time that the
credit idea comes in? Well, this is the
first case um after the second reference
in which it was it was an issue at all.
Yes, but it's in this case um
this is the first introduction of that
scientific is what's the first
introduction in the in the court
documents. It hasn't been pleaded or
anything appears here. No one's taking
any we're not taking any pleading point
on this. I'm trying to must be clear,
but we we're attempting to if you like
defend against a pleading point that
seems to be being taken that that we
didn't plead to any of this.
But there wasn't wasn't anything to to
plead to.
Now the the revenues case at this stage
was was that it was the as we still
maintain
was that there shouldn't be
disapplication. There shouldn't be
exemption but there should be a credit
for actual tax paid.
[Music]
And then if you look at what they say
about conforming interpretation
on paragraph 75,
this is in relation to ACT.
The present litigation concerns ACT paid
on the onward distribution by the UK
waters edge company of EU, a third
country source dividend income.
Following FI1, as interpreted by the
Court of Appeal, the claimants should be
entitled to a credit against their ACT
liability for the actual underlying tax
paid. Following FI2, this extends to
underlying tax paid further down the
route. Uh as you may have seen that
there was an issue in FII2 also about um
what we what we call the corporate roots
argument
uh as discussed above the claimants were
unable to provide underlying tax
information for the portfolio dividends
whether the water's edge or further down
the route. So can we just get clear
where the water's edge is? Um the W's
edge there are two sides of the channel
and the onward distribution by the UK
waters edge companies. Um, yes,
that's the first company which receives
a dividend from abroad. Yes, it's a
company on the UK. Yes, exactly. You
could have a an EU waters edge company
which is the company which remits the
dividend to the UK and absolutely a UK
one. Yes. Yes. And of course there there
would then typically there will be um
groups below below the W's edge and
there will be groups above the W's edge.
You you you have feeder companies which
may be uh
yes either downwards or onwards. Well
well very often groups will be
structured so that the trading companies
are near the bottom of the but the
bottom of the group and then they will
pass up profits by way of dividend um up
through various companies and then the
top company will usually be a holding
company that will simply be receiving
dividends from subsidiaries and then
paying them out to their shareholders.
That's the way the groups will be and
and the intermediate companies will be
there for various reasons perhaps tax
and other other reasons. Um but
sometimes it'll be quite can be quite a
few intermediate companies between the
the trading companies which actually
produce the profits and the the top
companies. They can be fed down a line
before it and at some point it crosses
the channel and um then it's distributed
here at some point in the UK. Yes. Yes.
Um shareholders. In FI we were looking
at groups of companies. So 100%
generally shareholding and the group
itself would have would have part across
the channel if you like and parts in the
UK. Um what we're looking at in this
case is portfolio holdings. So we're
looking at investments in groups which
have their top company um at the w's
edge across the channel if you like
and who then pay their pay dividends on
those portfolio holdings to the UK
company.
And and then we see um issue what is now
issue three
disc discussed at page 4232.
paragraph 82 uh 83 84
the issue of whether the claimant had a
claim in respect of lawful act utilized
against unlawful mainstream corporation
tax was debated in the code of appeal
and fi code of appeal the code of appeal
held that the claimant's restitutionary
remedy extended to lawful act utilized
against unlawful mainstream tax
on the basis act is an advanced payment
of the mainstream charge HMRC give
permission to appeal to the Supreme
Court.
This is one of the issues which the
Supreme Court has deferred his decision
on whether to give permission to appeal.
That that deferral continues as has been
continued by um this court until
well after this decision I think and so
they say pending the Supreme Court's
future decision whether to give
permission to appeal the court in the
present case is bound by the decision of
the court of appeal the claimments of a
resitutionary remedy and that that's
been the position below both before Mr.
Justice Henderson and of course before
the court of appeal as well but they
they were bound equally by the previous
court of appeal decision.
So that that's why this issue what is
now called issue three can only arise in
in this court. It it couldn't it
couldn't be argued below.
This is not an issue uh which um
is this an issue which was open in the
court appeal.
Um
in other words, was permission to appeal
given uh to the court of appeal given in
respect to this issue in this case? I
don't I don't think we went through that
process. It simply was assumed that it
would be they'd be bound by the the
decision of this of the previous court
of appeal. So the situation is we we
have a court of appeal judgment where
the issue has been debated and this
court at present hasn't decided whether
to grant permission to appeal that yes
that's right yes but this this court one
of the points made against you maybe not
in this context that's what I'm testing
is that uh we don't have jurisdiction to
deal with issues except by way of appeal
from the court of appeal if the issue
hasn't even got to the court of appeal
then there's a potential potential
problem. Is that a problem which arises
here?
Well, I mean you the normal way of
dealing with the point if you wanted to
challenge it in the Supreme Court and
there was binding authority at court of
appeal level against you would be to um
go to the court of appeal and say give
us permission. We know we're going to
lose but we want to go to the Supreme
Court. Did you do that? I'm not I I
can't I can't honestly remember exactly
what was said before the court of appeal
on this issue. What what what we do have
is an appeal against the if you like the
the the judgment which this issue
relates to i.e. the the the amount of of
tax that has to be repaid. We have an
appeal against that. So and and that
that well we have to focus a bit more on
it that that would effectively cover
that. I mean the fact and the fact that
you need you accept you need permission
to appeal I think in your in your
written case. So that uh
Yes, I think you can't it's not
sufficient simply to say it's covered by
a blanket. It's it either you either
need permission to appeal or you don't.
And uh in order to know whether you're
entitled to permission to appeal, we
have to understand a little bit more
about um um how far this issue is open
in this case as opposed to the FI
litigation. It may seem technical, but
we ought to get it right. Yeah, sure.
Yeah, I'll return to that. Yeah.
Um
so so that that is and and then you will
see that there was also
a question about how interest was
payable which is page 4255
and what basis is interest payable
and the argument there is for for
compound interest.
So that that that my lord is the
is the basis on which the trial was
conducted. Those issues were identified.
It wasn't conducted on the basis of
looking at what the pleadings said. Um
now part of that you'll see if if you
turn back my lord to MS 4227
paragraph 63 42 sorry 4227 4227
where this is the test claim's argument
as to why it should be the the nominal
rate of the of the W's edge company, the
foreign waters edge company.
Um,
a construction based on nominal rates
applicable to companies lower down the
corporate route would require reading in
a network of new detailed provisions
addressing the patterns of dividend
flows likely to exist below the W's
edge. Just to give a few examples, we
necessary to read in provision
determining how the relevant nominal
determined where profits were earned and
taxed in one or more countries and then
taxed again wholly or in part in another
country. where the profits were taxed in
the country where they were earned and
largely exempted in another state before
onward traition to the UK that this is
what I was mentioning earlier that it's
quite it's quite common that the
dividends received by the holding
company the waters ed company would be
exempt in that country from tax
what is often referred to as a a
participation exemption which which we
now have in this country as well where
the profits pass through a mix an
offshore mixer
For those in other scenarios, there need
to be detailed rules applying
specifically how the nominal rates of
tax were to be identified, ascertained
and apply
in the claimment submission. Such an
exercise would go far beyond the
permissible remount of the courts and
giving effect on ECJ ruling. It would be
grossly unfair,
virtually impossible to substantiate
their claims.
Now
what what you may you may be aware is
that that exercise precisely has been
done in FII
and again I'll come back to that because
Mr. Justice Henderson and FII decided
that the appropriate nominal rate to
look at was not the rate of the waters
edge company but was the rate of the
company
where the profits were actually
generated and tax was actually paid.
Well, there are some findings in this
case by him though, aren't there as to
the feasibility of yes, the PU doing
this exercise and um I I won't claim to
reproduce precisely his words, but he
basically said it would be impractical,
didn't he? He Well, we we'll look at
what the what the to look at what he
said, but he he he said it would be it
would be extremely extremely extremely
difficult. Yes, it could be expected of
them. Yes, I think the evidence Are we
bound by the findings in this case? We
can't um look at um um some finding in
another case even though it's a judge.
No, you're bound by the finding. I I'm I
quite agree, my lord. All I'm saying is
that it's not it's not to say it's an
exercise that goes far beyond the
permissible rewet of the courts and
giving an effect on EGCJ ruling is not
has turned out not to be correct because
both Mr. Justice Henderson and the Court
of Appeal have decided that you can and
must do that in in FII. That's that's
the only point I was making. As regards
this case, it's quite correct that he he
has said that it would be not be
expected of them. I think when you
actually look at the evidence, it it
wasn't that they did it and found it
impossible. It's simply they didn't do
it at all because they thought it would
be impossible. But but the point on that
is is very much the point Mr. Just as
Henderson himself made, which is
European law says that I'm afraid that's
simply part of the amputation system.
That's life. They say you can't do it
too bad. You ought to have arranged
beforehand to um uh that the information
would be given you. Yes. When it became
important, you you can't you can't pull
yourself up by your bootstraps and say
that the the system should be different
because we can't operate the system that
is
approved. And it's been said a number of
times by the European Court that the the
amputation system is perfectly valid and
it requires you to provide evidence of
if it requires you to provide evidence
of tax paid or of nominal rates below
then that's that is part of the system
and that that is one of the issues
precisely what that what the European
Court has said that that arises in in
the cross appeal.
But I I think it's important to bear in
mind
that
an an assumption that the that the W's
Edge company would actually have paid
tax is probably in a lot of cases an
unrealistic one
and it has to be accepted that by taking
the by taking the W's edge company that
that is being taken as a kind of well it
it it doesn't accord we would say and
we'll come back to this with the
reasoning of the European Court in FI
number two as to why a foreign nominal
raid was an appropriate thing to take
was an appropriate yeah was appropriate
it it the chord with that because and
again Mr. Justice Henderson recognized
that himself when he came to look at
this again in NFI and I I'll show you
that
one one has to one has to accept that by
taking the that for a nominal rate it
doesn't you're taking a rate that
doesn't necessarily have any connection
at all with tax that was actually paid
or char or indeed charged.
So I I I don't think it's ne I don't say
it's necessary for tax to be paid but at
least it has to be charged at a
particular rate. Well, presumably one
reason if you are looking at the tax uh
position of the
let's say the EU W's edge company and if
as you say such a company may well not
pay tax then I suppose it might be
logical to look at the
foreign national rate of tax
would that be uh I mean if it doesn't
actually pay tax and you you would have
to find if you are looking at it some
other um
tax rate than the actual one. Is that
part of the thinking or not? Well, what
um jump ahead what what what Mr. Justice
Henderson decided after looking at it in
more detail perhaps in FII was that what
you should be looking at should be
taking out is a foreign nominal rate
underneath of the company which actually
was paying tax and it was necessary to
go through quite a complex process. What
the two stages in that argument are the
firstly you're not looking at the W's
edge company you're looking at the
feeder companies which are supplying it
with dividends and secondly are you
looking at the actual rate of the feeder
companies
you're looking at the the the the we
call the nominal rate but it means the
rate as opposed to the effective rate
sorry my lord there's this distinction
between nominal and effective rates
perhaps so you are looking at the FNR
the FNR is the is the headline rate of
tax in the particular country, not the
effective. So, you look up and see it's
30% or 35% or whatever, but the the
effective rate of course is the is the
is the um is the rate produced by
expressing the amount of tax actually
paid by the company as a percentage of
its accounting profits. And that's
that's what we ought to be looking at
according to you your case as well. What
we ought to be looking at according to
our case on issue one is is the actual
tax. No, the actual tax paid. Is that
the effective rate? Well, you
computationally you can produce the same
result. Yes, you you can produce the
actual tax paid by applying the
effective rate to the to the um profits.
Yes, they all should be the same.
They're all part of the same
computation, Lord. Yes. Yes. Exactly.
But but you end up but what you're
actually giving credit for is the tax
paid against tax. Yes.
And and as as we said in our our
response case
what what we say about this is
you you have to decide at this stage
whether it is act clear
um the that the way in which the test
claimants and Mr. Justice Henderson
cited this is is correct
and that they rely on FI number two and
we we say simply if you look at FI
number two and understand it
doesn't support what they say.
Whatever the answer is is not what the
test claimments say it is.
I I I I
think I can put it this way. It it it it
appears that the the test claimant's
case is that there are two discrete
legal issues.
one is do you use a foreign nominal rate
or the actual tax paid a foreign nominal
rate any one you decide that issue then
completely separately you decide which
foreign nominal rate you use
um and and they say it's only the first
of these issues
that you can determine and you have to
accept that that the foreign nominal
rate is the rate of the edge company
And we say that's an impossible
contention because to understand why it
is a foreign nominal rate, you have to
understand which foreign a nominal rate
you're you're applying.
You can't you can't answer that question
in the abstract
without understanding the reasoning of
the code of justice. In the second
reference,
it it the Court of Justice didn't simply
say use a foreign nominal rate, any rate
you think appropriated.
It it it came to its conclusion by a
series of uh propositions and reasoning
which we we could look at.
Now, this is a point where there is an
objection.
You're raising it, isn't it? Well,
that's that's what I think is the
objection, my lord. I think the
objection is I'm trying to I'm trying to
explain. Yeah. They say, well, the only
issue here is is it a a foreign a
nominal rate or the actual tax. Yeah.
Right. And you cannot consider you say
you can't which rate it is. You just
decide it is a rate and then we know
what the rate is because that's been
decided um elsewhere. and and I and I
say well it's impossible to to do that
because to understand to answer the
question is it the foreign nominal rate
or the actual tax paid you have to
understand the reasoning not just um
apply a um linguistic analysis but you
have to understand the reasoning of the
code of justice in the second reference
um and as I say that that is the
conclusion as we'll see that Mr. Justice
Henderson himself came to when he looked
at it again
and we would say correctly.
So I I was proposing my lord to take you
now to the statutory provisions.
[Music]
They're in the f the first authorities
bundle
and it
the corporation tax provisions are I
would submit straightforward
corporation tax was at the time charged
on foreign dividends
that is dividends from nonUK residents
companies. Whereas dividends from UK
resident companies were exempt from tax
under what was then section 208 of
Victor.
So what page reference we're on? So
sorry, I was I would before I came to
the I was just going to say I wasn't
going to look at the corporation tax
provisions because they're pretty
straightforward. We we don't need to
look at those. But what we will look at
are the ACT provisions which are behind
tab eight of the bundle.
your lordships just on a small point may
may see reference to D5 tax. Um the
reason for that is that um going back to
the income tax system um foreign
dividends were charged under schedule D
case 5
um and and corporation tax was charged
according to income tax principles. So
it's it's always been referred to in
shorthand as as D5 income.
Of course, everything's changed now with
a corporation tax acts which consolidate
everything and don't refer to the income
tax
principles at all.
So, tabby 8 MS 4446
section 231
uh where a company resident in the UK
makes a qualifying distribution. The
person receiving the distribution is
another such company or a person
resident in the United Kingdom not being
a company. The recipient shall be
entitled to a tax credit equal to such
proportion of the amount or value of the
distribution as corresponds to the rate
of advanced corporation tax in force for
the financial year in which the distri
uh the distribution is made.
So that that provides the credit.
It provides a credit for both
um companies and individuals who receive
dividends.
The individuals receive the credit by
way of a at that time I think a credit
against basic rate income tax
essentially.
And and it was originally until I think
a repayable credit. So if if you if you
were someone who had no income for you
got it back. Yeah. You you got it back.
And similarly exempt pension funds etc.
got it back. That that's what changed in
1997. Um Gordon Brown.
Um so that that grants the credit and
act which we we'll go on to was was
in in was brought in in 1972
and the essential rationale of act
domestically if you like was was to fund
the tax credits.
that the problem was that corporation
tax was paid a good deal after the um
dividends would be paid
and in the meantime the recipients of
the dividends could claim the tax
credits and indeed the exempt
institutions
could claim a payment in cash
immediately.
quite quite a you you'll be aware my
laws that quite a large proportion of
public companies are owned by the exempt
institutions.
So the purpose of act was to ensure that
something was paid at the time the
dividend was paid in order to fund the
tax credit.
Um, and this was all looked at in a case
by the House of Lords in a case called
Pirelli, which you lodges may or may not
have heard something about, which was
part of the ACT litigation.
Uh, and essentially it was it was held
by the House of Lords that there was an
unspoken link between ACT and the tax
credit. um which meant essentially if
you didn't pay ACT, you didn't get the
tax credit that the the House of Lodge
held.
Um but ACT of course also operates as a
an advanced payment of corporation tax.
So if if we move on from section 231 to
section 238 which is MS 4464
[Applause]
this is part of the system for
collecting act
um franked investment income which is fi
means means income of a company resident
in the UK which consists of a
distribution respective which the
company's entitled to a tax credit
and frank payment means the sum of the
amount or value of a qualifying
distribution and uh the proportion or
the amount of values corresponds to the
rate of act
and and we'll see these concepts are
then used
in determining
when we come to look at at how ACT is
calculated
Before we get to that though, in order
section 239,
page 4467,
subject to section 497, which is not
relevant. Subsection two, advanced
corporation tax paid by a company and
not repaid in respect of any
distribution made by it in an accounting
period shall be set against its
liability to corporation tax on any
profits charged to corporation tax for
that accounting period and shall
accordingly discharge a corresponding
amount of that liability.
So that that is the set off provision in
relation to to act
and subsection four then tells you that
where there's a surplus advanced
corporation tax which is not set off you
carried it's treated as exactly it's
carried forward treated as paid in the
in the subsequent period
but just thinking aloud the the purpose
of the tax credit um in principle is is
to ensure that the the income is only
taxed once in the hands of the company
and not you don't have the same income
taxed a second time in the hands of the
recipient of a dividend. That's right.
Um yes. Um and so the the act is simply
affecting the timing of the company's
payment of the of of tax on its income
so that there is effectively a cash flow
which will finance the tax credits. That
that's the broad idea. Of course, it
doesn't it doesn't in practice always
work out like that because well what ACT
is often not set off against corporation
tax. If there if there is no tax
corporation tax liability or very small
um then act becomes surplus and is
carried forward. Yeah. So but that that
your your logic is right that's that's
conceptually the under underpinning of
it all. Um but the the problem which was
arising in relation to particularly
companies who had foreign income
um was that they didn't have any
corporate didn't have much corporation
tax liability on the foreign income
because of double tax relief basically
uh and um they they still were paying
ACT because they were distributing the
the foreign income to their
shareholders. So they had to pay ACT but
they didn't have a lot of corporation
tax to set it against. How how does that
work? Because I thought I mean you could
only you distribute dividends distribute
income out of um profits. Yes. But these
were profits which were not being taxed
in the UK.
So, so that that there were profits, but
there wasn't a a there wasn't a um
proportionate amount of corporation tax
being paid on the profits, mainly
because it was covered by double tax
relief.
So, within the UK system, this this
caused a buildup of of act.
And this was something that was if you
go right back to the white paper which
I'm not proposing to take you to but you
the white paper before the introduction
of act this was something that was
anticipated at the time that that might
happen. Let me just give us a reference
to that. Um I think I think it is in the
bundles actually. I'm not sure. I I'll
I'll I'll I'll find out but it's it's
not particularly relevant to the No, but
it just helps one um get the background.
Yes. Background.
So that then section 241 this tells you
how you calculate act
and where where a company receives
franked investment income
it's not liable to pay advanced
corporation tax in respect to qualifying
distributions paid by it in that period
unless the amount of the franked
payments made by it exceeds the amount
of that income.
And two, if an account is such an
excess, advanced corporation tax is
payable on an amount which when the
advanced corporation tax payable is
added to it is equal to the excess.
Um, and if it's a surplus of franked
investment income, that's also carried
forward.
So the way it works is that you you you
compare franked investment income coming
in and franked payments that is dividend
payments going out and if the frank
payments exceed the franked investment
income, you pay ACT on the on the
difference essentially.
So it's it's not that there is a
although sometimes in a loose way people
talk about a credit against act it's not
exact not actually how it works there
isn't actually an act liability
unless the frank payments exceed the
franked investment income
and just finally for completeness
because it's referred to in a number of
cases is section 247
is um the group income election
that this this allows companies within a
group to elect
that that a dividend paid by them
doesn't is not chargeable to act but but
then would not be franked investment
income
I'm not it's on page sorry it's on page
4492 to right
and what you what's the proposition this
helps you you
the well this explains also some of the
background to some of the cases because
um the ACT litigation for instance SERA
uh was actually all about group income
elections um yeah because what what was
what was argued in in um in HTH in the
SERA was there ought to be the the
possibility of making a group income
election even when you pay a dividend to
a non-resident company.
Now, of course, the result of that would
be there would simply been no ACT paid
at all anywhere because the non-resident
companies obviously are not liable to to
act. But that's what the European Court
held that it was a breach of um the
treaty freedom of establishment not to
allow UK subsidiaries of of um German
let's say parent companies to make a
group income election with the German
parent. So no ACT was paid and that that
led to the unlawful ACT charges in was
in for instance Serra. That was the
background to the the sea case and and
this is of course part of the system
because it ensures that ACT is only paid
at one level within a group.
Typically most cases it's paid at the
top but but in a few cases it's paid
lower down but it would generally be
paid at the top company level. The
reason one of the reasons for that is
you can only surrender ACT to
subsidiaries. You can't surrender ACT
upwards in the group.
So usually it would be arranged so that
all the payments up to the top company
were under group income elections.
Now we we don't have that in credential.
The structure in credential is very
simple. There were two companies. I
think the company we're dealing with
claimment is actually the waters ed
company and it did pay a considerable
amount of act. I couldn't hear that.
Sorry. it did pay a considerable amount
of act but I I think that may be because
it's an insurance company and there are
particular issues with insurance
companies
but but in the present case we don't
have the complexities of payments
through the group
we simply have receipts by the waters
edge company and then divides paid by
the waters edge company on which act was
paid
So th those are the statutory
provisions. Um,
and so now now what I was proposing to
take you through hopefully
relatively speedily
is is how the how the case law
developed.
Um
what um I I noticed in preparing this
case that I I don't think there is a a a
full chronology anywhere in the the
papers and I thought it might be helpful
to you. It's certainly helpful to me to
have a chronology. This this is simply a
chronology of when the various decisions
Well, I taken I I have to say I spent
some time writing one out. All right.
Certainly be I hope confir confirmatory.
Well, I would quite like it because I
didn't spend some time. Yes. Well, we we
have
um it's not agreed, but I don't think
it's controversial. I mean, it simply
states the dates on which decisions were
taken. Yes, it's very very helpful and
possibly with references as to where
they are as well. Um this one doesn't
but I think we can we could we can
easily provide that without it's quite
the I think the your your case has at
the beginning. Yes, we have a we have a
glossery at the beginning which I think
does that um
sorry
can I just ask to make sure I'm
following this that that um
the problem is um leaving aside group
income elections which we're not
concerned with directly here. The the
problem is is partly the one that you
mentioned earlier that um if you're
receiving your income from a foreign
company, um you're you're unlikely to
have much corporation tax to set your
ACT against
um but also that the income that you're
receiving isn't going to be franked
investment income and so you won't get
the um you'll be paying ACT on a whole
of it rather than simply the
um the the slice that would be taxable.
under section 241 if you were a um if it
were UK dividend income. Yes. Right.
Yes, that's right. And and I'll I'll
come on to that. But yes, ACT there are
slightly different issues in ACT but but
essentially that's that's the point my
lord. Yes. Um so the starting point um
are two references that were made. The
first in chronologically was a reference
in the FIGLO.
Uh and that was made on the 13th of
October 2004.
Um and I think we just ought to look at
the at least the questions that were
referred just to understand the
structure of that because we will have
to look at at the FII cases. It's in um
bundle seven of the authorities tab 70.
It's MS2689.
So the questions begin at the bottom of
of MS2689.
And as I mentioned earlier at this
point, but when we when we were agreeing
these references,
this reference we we really were at the
very beginning. We didn't we didn't have
any clue really what what the court of
justice was going to say and what what
the shape of the litigation was going to
be. Um but question one is is a question
about corporation tax.
It's a basic question and we'll see that
the answer to that question caused a lot
of difficulty
uh but it's essentially asking whether
it is contrary to article 43 to apply
measures which exempt from corporation
tax dividends received by a resident
company uh but but don't exempt
dividends
other dividends but provide double
taxation relief
both for withholding tax in all cases
and in some cases is for underlying tax
when it's talking about exemption is
that the exemption of 10% um
shareholdings
that's the exe the the exemption is the
the UK exemption so all all all UK
dividends oh yes of course are exempt
from the tax yes of course
uh and then the second question
it relates to act
that that's the point my lord lord read
is averting to
that that the
when they receive foreign dividends,
they're not they're not in any way FII.
Question three is a slightly esoteric
question, but it's it's it's it's asking
it's pointing out that you can surrender
ACT to UK resident companies, which they
can set against their corporation tax,
but you can't surrender it to nonUK
resident companies. Um, and the question
was, was that a breach of the treaty?
Um, and we'll see that the court came
back with an answer that the the test
claimants said was not the question they
had asked. So we it had to be this
question also had to be re-referred in
the second reference.
Um question four is about fids. I'm not
going to say anything about fids.
There's a lot about fids in fii but not
in this case. This was a method in 19
introduced 1994 to attempt to ameliate
the problem of of surplus act.
But I I'm unless your lordship's going
to warn you I'm not going to go into
bids. Um question five then was a
question about standstill provision that
that is a provision which relates to the
free movement of capital.
it it and what it says is where you have
uh movements between the UK or a member
state sorry and a third country
if there's been if there was a
restriction in force in 199 end of 1993
then you can continue to have that
restriction
the background to that was that it was
it was at that date that the free
movement of capital provisions were
extended to third countries outside the
EU
so there is this standstill provision
and and a questions arise have arisen in
the litigation as to whether there is a
new restriction after 1993 when when the
legislation changes etc. Now standstill
is not relevant in this case because
standstill provisions don't apply to
portfolio dividends.
They only apply to um basically at least
I think possibly 25% or more um holdings
but it's very important in the in the FI
case. And then finally there was a whole
lot of questions referred. You will see
questions seven, eight and nine all
about remedies
essentially asking whether various
claims were claims for repayment or were
damages claims.
Uh and and also
questions about factor tame whether
there was a sufficiently serious breach
which is question nine.
Um, so a whole lot of questions were
asked of the European Court.
Um, and and there was a similar
reference made
um that that was 13th October 2004. A
similar reference was made in the
present GLLO on the 18th of March 2005.
and and that is
that can be seen in the core volume.
The um so the reference in the present
case is in the core volume at tab 10 at
the back.
It it begins on MS 3716
and and the questions are on 3721.
So again the so the first question is a
general question about corporation tax.
Uh the second question is a particular
question relating to corporation tax and
insurance companies
which a lot of the a number quite a
number of the um claimants in this in
this GLO were insurance companies. Um
then question three is about something
completely different which is controlled
foreign companies legislation.
which which is why this GLO is called
the CFC and dividend GLO related to two
things. We don't have to we don't have
to um we're not at all interested in the
CFC provisions.
Um uh and then there was a question
about third countries. Was there any
difference if it was for the countries?
That's question four.
And a question about standstill
provisions again. Question five.
Uh and then again 6 7 8 9 and 10 uh 11
and 12
were all questions about remedies.
And the the answer it came back in FII
on the 12th of December 2006. That was
when the judgment of the court was
delivered that we've been looking at in
bundle 7.
Right. What what page? Um well we were
looking we were looking at the judgment.
It was tab tab 70 beginning 2679 it
begins on that's that's the judgment of
the court in II
and um it came the answer to question
one is one that we we have to look at
again when we come to
um FI Number two,
essentially it it sent back a question
to the national court,
which was whether the the rates of tax
which it referred to in the judgment
were the were indeed the same in the UK.
Wait, where was that? It's
It deals with Sorry, a lot.
It begins dealing with question one on
page 2695
and then
it it gives it conclusions are on page
2707.
2707. 2707.
And the probably the best place to find
the question is on page 2702, paragraph
56.
It's for the national court to determine
whether the tax rates are indeed the
same and whether different levels of
taxation occur only in certain cases by
reason of a change in the tax base as a
result of certain exceptional reliefs.
and so and and that was the question
that caused the controversy
because the difficulty when we came back
to the the high court
the was determining what the what the
question meant I What what does the
question mean? The application to the
company making the distribution
and the company receiving it. Just just
fit those into the chain. Which which
are they? Sorry, which paragraph are you
looking at? Paragraph 55, the previous
paragraph, which leads into 56, doesn't
it? Yes.
Well, that was all part of the the
puzzle in this case. What um what nobody
could what no one could understand is
why the European Court were confused by
this point. Um
the what are
the different levels of taxation the
company making the distribution that's
the foreign company is it the foreign
waters edge company and the company
receiving it is no what no no in in this
what what they're looking at my this is
quite important what they're focusing on
is dividends paid between UK companies
yes I see the paragraph 54 seems to be
the the the point that they're
discussing Yeah. So, so they're asking
the question where a UK company
subsidiary pays a dividend to its parent
company. Yes, I see. Um,
are the rates of tax the same
that the subsidiary pays and the parent?
Yes. Because if the subsidiary pays an
actual rate of tax which is less than
the nominal rate, then the exemption is
giving something different from what
would be given if they were both paying
the same nominal rate. Well, that's the
reasoning of the European Court. Yes.
Yes, my lord. That's what they come
through. That's that's what that's what
they say. What they Yes.
Um what they seem to be saying is that
there won't be equivalent treatment
if if a UK company
pay subsidiary paying to its parent um
is ex the dividend is exempt even though
the subsidiary pays tax at a lower
effective rate than the the nominal rate
of tax
assuming I think that the parent will
pay tax at the nominal rate
essentially. Okay,
that that's the reasoning. I don't I
don't I don't I don't say it's
necessarily so I mean the reason sound
reasoning but is the reasoning on the
assumption that they are the same
you can forget about the problem and um
simply give a credit by way of
exemption. That's if I think I think
we're saying if if they are the same
then there's equivalent treatment and
therefore the um yes you you you you
it's fine to give credit for actual tax
paid
and the and the difficult question was
what what was meant by the rates of tax
because if if you read the whole of I'm
not going to take you through it but
because this is of purely historical
interest now but if you look for the
read through for the judgment it's not
at all clear whether they're referring
to the nominal rates or or effective
rates
And
what happened was Mr. Just there was
then an argument in the high court
um as to what the question meant
essentially. It it was agreed
uh the answer was agreed. It was simply
the question that was the problem. If
the question was were the nominal rates
the same then the answer was clearly
they were. Nobody disputed that. If the
answer was is the effective rate paid by
the subsidiary
less in some cases more than more than
more than merely exceptional cases is it
less than the nominal rate the answer
was clearly yes it was
there's no doubt UK companies have
reliefs and exemptions and whatever for
tax purposes that are not reflected in
the um the computation of the profits
for accounting purposes.
So there's no doubt
in in any in fact in any developed
system of tax that the there will be
differences between the effective rate
for tax purposes and the nominal rate.
So that was the question. Mr. Justice
Henderson decided
well just jumping slightly ahead. He
decided when it came back uh that it
that it meant the effective rate and
therefore he concluded that the UK
provisions were unlawful in their
entirety
and and therefore would be disapplied.
So the conclusion that Mr. Justice
Henderson came to the first time round
was that there should effectively be a
complete exemption for um EU dividends
coming from dividends coming from EU
countries
not for not not not for third country
dividends because the the standstill
provision applied to those but but EU
dividends
um
and that was then that then went to the
court of appeal and the the court of
appeal were divided the majority thought
that that we were right, that he was
referring to nominal rates. Um, the
minority thought that Mr. Justice
Anderson was right. And the Court of
Appeal therefore decided to refer the
question back to the Court of Justice
and that that that's what became the
second reference.
We'll return to that when we look at we
look at the um ECJ2.
Um the answer to the second question on
ACT
you will find
at paragraph 112
MS2717
and and
This was it was
article 43 and 56 precluded legislation
which allows a resident company
receiving dividends for another resident
company to deduct from the amount which
the former is liable to pay by way of
act the amount of tax paid by the latter
company
whereas no such deduction is permitted
in the case of a resident company
receiving dividends from non-resident
company. Now the comparison there that
the European Court was drawing was
between a UK company which pays a
dividend to its parent without a group
income election and therefore pays act
and the payment is therefore franked
investment income
and the court was regarding that as
being essentially a deduction of the tax
paid. Now we've seen that that's not
exactly how the system worked but that's
how they conceptualized it.
uh that the parent was able to deduct
the ACT that's paid by the subsidiary
in computing its ACT liability.
But a non-resident subsidiary paying to
a UK parent, the UK parent could not
deduct any of the tax liability tax
payments by the subsidiary from its act.
So that that's the that's the
comparison.
The the question then arose on when the
matter went back.
It was assumed at that stage that this
meant that you had to grant a credit for
tax paid foreign tax paid against ACT.
That's what it appears to have been
saying. Um,
but the question was, did it only refer
to the tax paid by the top company, the
company that was paying the dividend,
the W's edge company, or did it did it
refer also to tax paid further down the
the chain,
the European Court decision appeared to
only refer to the tax company paying and
that that was the corporate roots
argument, which you'll see
referred And that was another question
Mr. Justice Henderson decided to refer
to the European Court as a result of the
first hearing
and uh that was appealed but all the
courts above confirmed that the
reference should take place. So there
was that that was one of the questions
that was referred
and as I said the answer to this in this
um in FII came back on the 12th of
December 2006
following that and another another case
in relation to CFC's called Cadbury
Schweps which was a separate case which
also was referred to the European Court
the court then wrote to the parties
in the CFC case and asked whether we
wanted to maintain the reference.
Whether you wanted to sorry maintain the
reference. Um and the answer that came
back was that we did or the the national
court said it wanted to maintain the
reference. Um and you can see that
recorded in the judgment of the court in
the CFC case
core volume tab 10.
[Music]
Um, page 3723.
You can see paragraph 33. The referring
court informed the court it was
maintaining its reference.
And then 34 under the first subp
paragraph of 1043 where a question
referred to the court for preliminary
ruling is identical to a question on
which the court has already ruled or
where the answer to such a question may
be clearly deduced from existing case
law. The court may after hearing the
advocate general at any time give its
decision by reasoned order
by hearing the advocate general. I think
they just they just mean talking to him.
There is there is no advocate general
opinion in this. This is the court's
attempt to give a a stuffy answer to uh
a reference which uh it it believes it
the answer is obvious. Yes. Although it
took
132 paragraphs to say it to say that.
Yes.
Yes. But this this is
it's one of the points that we make
which is
it is slightly peculiar that the court
of justice should have considered the
answer was could be clearly deduced from
the case law in in this reference when
when according to the test claimment's
case um they didn't give the correct
answer the full answer to the question
in in this
what they gave here what what the test
claims say is you have to you have to
read this as being modified by what they
decided subsequently. So essentially
what's being said is the answer they
gave here although they thought it was a
clear it was so clear that it could be
dealt with by a without a without a
hearing without an advocate general
opinion by a by a reasoned order
um it was so clear it was actually wrong
essentially
but were the um problems of
interpretation of the um earlier ruling
um raised with the court in this second
reference
Not that I'm aware of. No. No. I only
ask cuz there was a a gap of about um 16
months between the the the dates of a
two well a judgment in the first case
and a reasoned order in the second. Yes.
Although if we if we then look at um
the hearing well the hearing in the high
court where first arose was actually in
July 2008. Yeah. So it was it was after
this judgment was given.
Um and and the answers that were given
as I said the the first question
related was it was a general question
about corporation tax and the answer
they gave repeated
pretty much verbatim what was said in
the FI reference. You can you can see by
just glancing down that they're
referring constantly to which page are
we on now? Um sorry it begins my lord at
page 3723
the first question
and continues
till 3725.
And and you can you can note that even
even in this decision when it comes to
the
the um holding at the end paragraph 43
which is the answer.
There is a distinction drawn between
the portfolio holdings which is the
bottom
less than 10% voting rights
um and the others above it.
And then when we come to the question
the second question
which is specifically about the
insurance companies
you'll see that the the structure is
um again following to some extent FI.
The first question was the first issue
for them was whether it should be
article 56 or 43 and they decided
paragraph 52 it should be article 56
[Applause]
and then
then they consider the uh in between
paragraphs 53
and 57 they consider the issue of an
election insurance company could make.
And the question was whether that
was contrary to article 56
and paragraph 56 they say in the regard
it's not apparent from the decision
making the reference whether in the
light of the fact the permitted election
as regards dividends of national origin
entailed the waiver of tax credits a
company receiving dividends of foreign
origin which could not exercise such an
election was treated less favorably
because of that fact alone. It's for the
national court to establish whether such
was the case.
The the point there was that the um the
dividends to the insurance company were
in fact UK dividends were
primacy taxed but there was an ability
to elect for them to be exempt which
then meant that they didn't receive tax
credit that they would otherwise have
received and the question was whether
allowing that election to take place was
more favorable treatment for for UK
dividends and the court said it was back
send it back to the national court to
determine that. It it then says in
paragraph 58, it's clear on the other
hand since it's clear from the decision
making the reference that companies with
less than 10% shareholding in the
company making the distribution were not
entitled to relief in respect of
corporation tax paid by that company in
the member state in which it was
resident. Those companies were contrary
to article 56 subject to less favorable
tax treatment.
So
they're making the point that there was
less favorable treatment simply because
of the lack of corporation tax the
relief for corporation tax paid abroad.
Um
and the UK then argue were arguing that
it was proportionate and legitimate to
restrict the availability of relief for
various reasons in respect of
um the difficulties
of um determining the tax which is
paragraphs 59 60 and 61. one
and that was rejected as being a a
justification for the difference of
treatment.
Um, and then beginning at paragraph 64,
you can see the UK contends the
difference in treatment is justified by
the need to ensure the cohesion of the
tax system
and and that is rejected
at paragraphs
67 and 68.
And then paragraph 60, the answer to the
second question must be article 56 is to
be interpreted as meaning it precludes
legislation on member state which allows
an exemption from corporation tax for
certain dividends received from resident
companies by resident insurance
companies but excludes such an exemption
for similar dividends received from
non-resident companies in so far as it
entails less favorable treatment of the
latter dividends
and the and the less favorable treatment
was obviously as as they've expressed
earlier not granting the credit for
corporation tax foreign corporation tax
uh and and then the they go on to
consider uh CFC's and the third sorry
the third question considers third
countries and then the fourth question
considers CFCs which we're not we're not
concerned
So
we would submit all all that you can
draw from the
the answer to the reference in the
present case
is that
there is less fiber treatment by not
providing a credit in respect of
corporation tax paid
abroad.
And the justification
of the need to ensure fiscal cohesion is
not not available.
Now we can perhaps look at
chronologically what happened next which
was Mr. Justice Henderson's this um
decision in the high court. Yes. Um
which is tab authorities 5
par uh sorry tab 53 um it begins MS1565
Now, there have been two rounds of
hearings before Mr. Justice Henderson in
the FIKS.
The first of those was was this this
this hearing. And you can see if you
turn to page
MS1565,
you can see the the legal issues
that Mr. Justice Henderson had to
determine.
There are
quite a few of them as you can see. Um
the way this this part of the
the hearing took place, the way it was
organized was was to
have a
in in this context fairly skeletal set
of facts which were simply a basis for
Mr. Justice Henderson to decide
a number of issues of law which clearly
were going to arise in in general in the
GLO. What then happened was well there
was an appeal on those issues to the
court of appeal. Uh and then then there
further appeal we'll come back to that
to the Supreme Court. But
after that when we came back to Mr.
Justice Henderson the second time. Um
the way it was organized was by an
actual trial
of of a of the bat claim, the British
American tobacco claim
um which
raised a whole lot of other legal issues
but but was argued on the basis of the
actual facts of that case. So it was it
was if you like more like credential
but at this stage it's it's being argued
almost as preliminary points um
because clearly a very large number of
legal issues still arose which had to be
determined. Um and and for these
purposes
the main issues of interest are issue
one
the the the D5
and issues 3 one and two questions
relating to ACT
um uh and also
the remedies issue in particular
issue three restitution or damages.
So what Mr. Justice Henderson decided
as I've already indicated on on on issue
one was that
the the the charge was unlawful
in its entirety
because he he decided that what the
European Court were referring to was the
was the effective rates and because the
effective rate was not not the same as
the nominal rate. Um, and that that
meant that that particular let out
didn't apply and and the European Court
had not mentioned any other letouts or
or qualifications at that stage. We'll
see that that changes when we come to
the second reference. But at that stage,
they had not said anything further.
Um, they had not dealt with the fiscal
cohesion argument at all in the in the
first reference. It wasn't even
mentioned.
Then on the on the corporate tree
points, he decided to refer these
questions to the European Court.
But he did decide
as a matter of conforming interpretation
um that
assuming tax was paid
abroad
um all of the foreign dividends or the
EU dividends would be should be treated
as FII. Hi.
So he he held it wasn't a question of
giving credit foreign tax or anything
like that that they would simply treat
the entire dividend as FII and and
operate the UK system as if it was FII.
And as regards remedies, he decided
that the point is relevant to this case.
He decided that various reliefs that
were given
where the taxpayer was saying that they
had wasted reliefs because they had set
reliefs against what was now known to be
unlawfully charged corporation tax.
that the claimants did not have a
restitutionary claim in respect of those
I using the word in better commas wasted
reliefs
that that any claim that they did have
would be in damages and and that
included at that stage act. So Mr.
Justice Henderson held that where where
ACT was set against unlawful corporation
tax again there was no claim in
restitution
a relief is not a disbbursement. to
relief is um um loss of an opportunity.
Exact. Yes. Exactly my lord. Um so
there's no there's no in putting it in
terms of unjust enrichment. There's no
enrichment of the revenue at that at
that point. Yes,
it is of course possible
that there may be a knock-on effect. In
other words, that that the taxpayers
would not if if they had known, they
wouldn't have used the relief there.
They would have used it somewhere else
and therefore
there would be a loss in that sense. But
that he said was not a claim in unjust
enrichment. it was a potentially a claim
in damages if you could show that
because you had because you had um
because there had been an unlawful
charge you had set your relief against
the corporation tax and you would
actually have set it against something
else somewhere else in the group or at
some other time something like that. So
that that that's the but that wasn't the
claim that was it's too indirect I
suppose is another way of putting it. I
mean it depends on circumstances and
perhaps choice. Exactly. Well that that
was I think the way Mr. Justice Henson
put it. It was a matter of and it's the
way the European Court had also
differentiated between
repayment claims and
Frankovich claims. The question of
whether there was a decision made by the
taxpayer.
So what the European Court broadly said
was you if if you if there's unlawful
charge you get back all the tax you paid
as a in response to the unlawful charge
and anything connected with that for
instance interest or penalties that you
might have paid
but you don't you don't you don't get
back you're not entitled to back as a
repayment claim or restitution
um things that are more indirect
and resulted from exercises of decisions
or judgment by the taxpayers.
So this this was the this was what is
partly part of this was what is now
issue three here.
So that that was what Mr. Justice
Henderson decided and then there was an
appeal from that to the court of appeal
and you can see again if you turn this
is on this is behind tab 54 begins on
MS1699
[Music]
and if you turn to 1716
you will see um an index
of the judgment which sets out all the
various issues that were determined
and there were there were 23 you can see
legal issues had to be determined.
So a as regards issue one as I've
already mentioned court of appeal
decided the a majority would have
decided the case the other way but they
they felt that it was right to refer the
matter since there was a disagreement
and they confirmed the references in
relation to the corporate roots points
in relation to act
uh as regards the restitutionary sorry I
haven't got that point you dropped your
voice I'm sorry uh Um, they confirmed
I'm very sorry, my lord. I I'm slightly
struggling with um my throats. I I'll
make every effort to to speak up. Sorry.
Uh but um they confirmed the corporate
roots references that had been made by
Mr. Justice Henderson, i.e. in relation
to ACT, whether you took account of
foreign tax only at the W's edge or
whether you took account of it further
further down as well. They they they
decided that that should be referred. In
other words, they dismissed the appeal
against the the reference. You said the
majority. Um, no. Uh, sorry. It was only
the majority on issue one. On issue on
on the all the other issues, they were
unanimous.
On issue one,
there was a division of opinion as to
what the correct answer was. Where does
that appear? Um well done you can you
can see it um from the headnote first of
all on page 1707
where it it says held one m largest
effort and dissenting.
Yes.
And I think you would find it probably
it's just at the end. Yes, I see. Yes.
Well, that's identified. Yeah.
So, yes, Lady Justice Arden and Lord
Justice Stanley Burnon agreed one way
and Lord Justice Ethan thought the other
way and and the reasoning was set out I
think in an annex to the the judgment.
Yeah. It's on page 1809
annex3 the differing analyses in answer
one
between the majority and minority
but anyway again this is of historical
interest only because we now have the
European court decision on this point.
So
what the judges thought
previously is not not really relevant.
Uh but then but then crucially on the
restitutionary issue
that is issue 13
which begins at paragraph 175.
The court of appeal the court of appeal
agreed with Lord sorry Mr. Justice
Henderson in relation to reliefs other
than ACT. They those were not
restitutionary claims but they held that
the position was different as regards
act.
and
that's the decision that has been
binding
so far and they decided it on the basis
I think the short basis that the
European Court regards ACT as being a
prepayment of corporation tax
that that is conceptually how the
European Court has looked at ACT
but of course as we shall see when we
come to this issue that that doesn't
answer the the question the the
restitutionary question
in English law whether
where lawful ACT is set against unlawful
corporation tax whether there's any
enrichment
of of the revenue.
Sorry in in the court appeal here is
upholding the judge on this point. It
appears paragraph 179 it is it upheld
the judge on on all the parts apart from
act
apart from ACT. 82 and where where is it
different? Well 179 at the beginning in
our judgment the only relief capable of
being restored as an unjust enrichment
is the application of MCT against the
case 5 charge that is for the reasons we
have given a sanio claim is to regarded
an advanced payment of MCT
utilization of the other reliefs may
have been a detriment to the claimments
but did not represent a gain to the
revenue for the purpose of a
restitutionary cause of action and then
then they go into deal. So that's the
one point where So that's the one point.
Yes.
Yes. Which differs from him. But are
they talking about setting it off
against
unlawful? Yes. They're talking about
unlawful case five. Yeah. Has all of all
of this is talking about setting reliefs
etc against unlawful case five.
So obviously if they set against lawful
case five there isn't any problem.
There's no problem at all. Yeah.
But we're talking about we are talking
importantly about lawful ACT. That is
having gone through the process of
determining which ACT is lawful and
which is unlawful. It's been determined
that this particular ACT was was
lawfully charged.
So there would be no question of
recovering the ACT itself when it was
charged because it was perfectly
lawfully charged. The question is
whether something happens when it's set
off against or purports to be set off
against unlaw an unlawful charge to
corporation tax.
Now you you will have seen that our our
primary contention about this is that
there simply was no there was no set off
at that time because the the provision
for set off section 239 only applies
where there is a liability to
corporation tax um and there was there
was no you say there can't have been a
benefit to the revenue
because um the act um remains chargeable
and remain they can still reclaim it
against um some future corporation tax.
This is an ineffective transaction.
That's that's correct. Setting it off
against an unlawful charge is another.
Yes. And and as we shall see, that is
the way that um the set off of act
against unlawful
corporation tax has been treated
by um Mr. the parties and Mr. versus
Henderson in general that that um
unlawful ACT sorry that's how unlawful
ACT set against unlawful corporation tax
has been treated. So the way that that's
been treated is the unlawful ACT remains
unutilized
because nothing happened because the
there was no charge to corporation tax
to to set it against. So whether it's
been unlawful ACT charged, even if it
has been purported to be said against
unlawful CT, it's treated for these
purposes as remaining outstanding. So
that the the the taxpayers are able to
claim the the full amount of the ACT
back with interest, not not just a sea
amount, that is an amount computed on
the basis of set off.
Um I'll I'll come back to that but
that's an important
part of the argument that that that is
the way that it's been treated and we'll
see Mr. Justice Henderson sets that out
in in the credential judgment itself.
Your lordship is
being puzzled.
No, I'm sure there are lots of things
that are going to
Can I just ask you I mean I have to
confess I not find it terribly easy to
keep up with all this. Is it is there
any of the does the court of appeals set
all this out with reasonable clarity or
where's the best account of what's been
going on? Well, the the problem is
that that two of these issues were not
considered by the court of appeal. I
understand that's for different reasons.
Well, perhaps for the same reason or in
your case. Yes, that's right. Um the the
only the only place in which the
compound interest point restitution has
been fully considered is Mr. Justice
Henderson's judgment in this case which
he then followed in little roots. So but
we're going all through this for what
purpose? I mean well the reason for
going through this get to the point and
see how it's dealt with for our
purposes. Yes. Well, it's necessary, I
think, sorry, to understand the
background because when you look at, for
instance, the second reference, it isn't
very obvious what's being decided unless
you understand where it's come from. Why
why they're deciding those questions.
Um, that that's the only reason for
looking at I thought I understood your
case. I'm not quite sure what's happened
this morning has made it clear. Well, I
that would be that was wonderful. If if
if um if I could just um rely on my case
and sit down, it would be fine. um
the the court of appeal decision. Then
there have been there were appeals by
both sides from the decisions of the
court of appeal
uh or rather applications for permission
to this court on on virtually all the
issues most of the issues on both ways.
the the issue that you you have heard in
my lord Lord Reed and Lord Sumption were
involved. I think you you heard some of
these appeals particularly in relation
to limitation and whether certain
limitation provisions were contrary to
EU law. Uh but there were other issues
um also decided in relation to de do
domestic matters. Um in particular
um whether
section 32 1A required
um that that there be a mistake as an
element of the cause of action or
whether it was sufficient. Oh, sorry. 1
C 31C whether it was sufficient that
there was a mistake in the background of
the case and this court decided
confirming a line of authority that it
had to be an element in the in the cause
of action and this is why crucially it's
essential for um the test claimants and
all the claimants in these GLOs's to
bring their claims within mistake of law
restitution that is unjust enrichment on
the basis of mistake
uh and I'll come back to that because
that's important in some of the some of
the later issues to to focus that that
these claims are all broad in mistake.
Um so th those issues were determined.
There was a further reference made by
this court in relation to the limitation
issues but I don't think we need to look
at that because I don't think it's
relevant for the present cases. That's
the third reference in FII.
Um
other issues remain outstanding.
Um the the court decided to adjourn I
think was the term used I can't remember
consideration of the permission
applications pending all these things
coming back from the European court. We
then I think went back to the court
after the court of appeal decision in
FII the second time around making
further applications and the court
decided to again put it all off until
after first of all Littlewoods which
this court has heard and decided but
then also this this case.
So I think the position is that after
this case is decided there will have to
be a decision made by by this court as
to whether or not to grant permission on
various issues which remain from the
first time round with the court of
appeal and the second time round with
the court of appeal in FII there's quite
a lot of the issues now some of these
issues might be decided to uh by this
court now
um but there there's likely to be some
issues still remaining
outstanding.
But that that's where we are
procedurally. That's why we're in this
claim. Slightly strange position that
there are decisions in another case
which are affecting um the decision in
this this case. They've all been been
carried on in parallel at different
times.
Um
[Applause]
so the reference Yes. Sorry, we've moved
on from the the that that paragraph. Um,
we were looking at where the court
appeal overruled or came to a different
view from Mr. Justice Henderson in FII
because
we we'll come back to this subject. Yes,
certainly. Yes. I was going to come back
to to issues. Well, I'll be able to put
the question which puzzled me to you
then. Okay. Yes. Well, I hope I can I
can I what I'll do is show you what Mr.
Justice Henderson said about all of this
in in credential which might might make
it clearer.
Um so the reference was made the second
reference which we're going to have to
look at in a moment was made by Mr.
Justice Henderson at the end of December
2010.
Um in February 2011
there was a judgment in Haribo
and and
that is quite that is obviously an
important case in relation to to issue
one.
Um,
Haribo was a case which concerned
entirely was entirely concerned with
portfolio dividends
and it's in sorry that's
did not happen.
It's in um bundle seven of the
authorities
behind tab 63
[Music]
before we look at it. C can I just
summarize
the position in Austria which you need
to understand
to understand this this reference.
Um the Austrian legislation at the
commencement of proceedings
provided for exemptions from corporation
tax in in three situations broadly. One
is domestic dividends. So it's very
obviously very similar to the the UK
system in that respect.
Secondly, dividends from EA countries
which had comprehensive procedures for
mutual assistance
with regards to administrative matters
and and enforcement which is becomes
important subject to an exception where
the foreign company wasn't subject to
equivalent tax to that in Austria
um or it was 10% less than Austria or it
was exempt. So you had to look at the
circumstances of the dividend paying
company in the state in which it was
paying it to determine whether it was
entitled to the exemption in Austria.
That's the second situation. In the
third situation, dividends from
shareholdings of at least 25%
which was then reduced retrospectively
to 10% later held for one year
subject to an exclusion to prevent
evasion or avoidance and to an exception
where the foreign company is not subject
again to equivalent tax as in Austria or
enjoys some kind of exemptions.
So again, they had to demonstrate what
the position was in the other another
country. And it was it was that
was one of the aspects that caused the
problem in Haribo because it was being
said by taxpayers.
We just we're dealing with portfolio
holdings. We've got very small
shareholdings in these companies. We
simply cannot find this information out.
It's it's extremely extremely difficult
if not impossible to actually get the
information and therefore to be entitled
to the exemption.
and we will see that the European Court
essentially said that's part of the
imputation system essentially
um otherwise so where it wasn't exempt
credit was given for actual tax paid
abroad except for dividends from
companies established in non-member
state parties to the EA
uh if there was no comprehensive
agreement in which case you didn't get
anything at
Um
in June 2008
there was an administrative notice which
has become quite important in this case
um which provide for a simplified
procedure for providing evidence of the
foreign tax paid. We we'll look at that.
We'll look at what is said about it in
the in the judgment of the court.
Um, Haribo received dividends from
portfolio holdings in companies
established in both member states and
non-member states and they applied to
the Austrian revenue for exemption from
tax
presumably on the basis of European law
as opposed to domestic law and that was
refused and they appealed to the
Austrian tribunals.
um the referring tribunal which is the
low the lowest tribunal held that the
dividend should be treated as exempt.
So they essentially came up with the
decision that Mr. Justice Henderson had
come with. The Austrians uh authorities
appealed to the administrative court
which allowed the appeal and held it was
appropriate to apply not the exemption
method but the method consisting of
crediting against Austrian tax the tax
which was charged in the state of
residence on the company paying the
dividend. And you you find all of this
what I've just been saying between
paragraphs 9 and 17 in the judge report.
The matter was referred back to the
um referring tribunal
by the administrative court which then
referred questions to the European court
and and and and during that process the
European court itself ref requested
clarification from the Austrian courts
as regarding the 2009 legislative
amendments that I I mentioned.
Um now the questions which were asked
are set out at paragraph 25 of the
judgment.
Sorry I I ought to have said what the
administrative court seem to have done
is is applied a conforming
interpretation very much like the the UK
courts to their own legislation. that is
they they said that in in conformity
with European law uh they would
interpret it as as granting a credit for
the tax paid. That was I think the
mechanism by which that that was
achieved.
So the questions at paragraph 25 and the
decision
of the court proper starts at paragraph
um 39.
the answer to the questions.
So the first question concerned
dividends from EA companies with no
comprehensive agreement for mutual
assistance.
Um and the question there was was that
was it was it a legitimate condition
that there should be such a agreement an
agreement for mutual assistance.
um the the first the first couple of
pages of this from paragraph 40 to 45
are not relevant. They're simply um
asking question of admissibility of the
question. And then the substance starts
at paragraph 46.
Um and
essentially what the what the court
concluded was that that it it was
justifiable to have a requirement
that there should be a comprehensive
agreement in relation to administrative
matters because that was relevant in the
amputation system to determining what
the actual amounts of tax etc paid in
the other state. But it wasn't
legitimate to require that there be uh
an agreement in relation to enforcement
because enforcement was not relevant to
the amputation system.
And you can see that if you turn on to
page 2465, MS 2465
at the bottom, paragraph 74.
[Music]
uh and also paragraph 73 you can see the
court is making the point that what is
necessary what might be necessary is is
a an agreement in relation to um
administrative matters but not in
relation to enforcement. So, so the
answer to the question in paragraph 75
is that um it wasn't permitted to have
that um condition.
Uh then question two and what what
question two this is a this was
important question because this
concerned what was called the switch
over from exemption to imputation system
where the taxpayer couldn't provide the
information which the Austrian
legislation required
and um the taxpayer
and and indeed the referring court I
think were making the point that this it
was almost impossible to provide this
information.
Um
you can see the requirement is set out
at paragraph 79 on page 2467.
only where the recipient of the
dividends has evidence relating to the
level of tax to which the companies
distributing such dividends are subject
in the state in which they are resident.
And it was held that that was a a
restriction in principle paragraph 81,
but that it was justified.
And this was on the basis that it was it
was legitimate to have both an
imputation system and an exemption
system
following FI1.
And
that's paragraphs
85, 86,
87, and 88.
And then paragraph 89.
In those circumstances, the amputation
method enables dividends from
non-resident companies to be accorded
treatment equivalent to that accorded by
the exemption method to dividends paid
by resident companies. Application of
the imputation method to dividends from
non-resident companies makes it possible
to ensure that foreign sourced and
nationally sourced portfolio dividends
bear the same tax burden in particular
with the state from which the dividends
come applies in the context of a
corporation tax a lower tax rate than
that applicable in the member state
where the company receiving the
dividends is established. In such a
case, exempting dividends from
non-resident companies would give
taxpayers that have invested in foreign
holdings an advantage compared with
those having invested in domestic
holdings.
So what the court's saying and they
repeat this in a number of other cases
is that you it's not required to give an
exemption in these circumstances.
What you what you do have to is you have
to apply an amputation system of some
sort
because giving an exemption goes too
far.
And then 90. In the light of the
equivalence between the exemption
imputation methods, the difficulties the
taxpayer might encounter in order to
prove that the condition for the tax
exemption of dividends received from
non-resident companies are met are in
principle irrelevant when determining
whether article 63 precludes legislation
such as that issue in the main
proceedings.
The only consequence of those
difficulties or even impossibility for
the taxpayer so or even impossibility he
says for the taxpayer to furnish the
proof saw will have is that the
imputation method which is equivalent to
the exemption method will be applied to
the dividends which the taxpayer
receives from non-resident companies.
Have I got it correct? Now the
argument really centers on what is said
in or paragraph 89 or derise from that
objection in paragraph 89 is that um
there is a risk that if you exempted
non-resident company dividends
um you would in fact be
giving um an advantage to taxpayers who
receive receive them because the
non-resident company might in fact have
paid tax at a lower tax rate. Yes. But
than a domestic company. And and the am
I right the debate has now moved on to
the um problem that in fact um the
domestic exemption or the tax credit
which recipients of dividends received
received used to receive uh which
enabled them to claim cash in those
days. um operated or could operate at a
higher rate than the company um making
the domestic dividend payments had
actually paid.
Is that is that that right? In other
that it was pointed out that this
problem also rised operated at a
domestic level. Uh
the problem of the problem of uh a
divergence between the um um
the the amount of um the benefit which
was being given to the um um
I think you'll have to take it through.
I I think the point that's being made in
paragraph 89, my lord, is simply that if
you if you grant exemption to to foreign
dividends Yes. um then you might be you
might be um an advantage because the
foreign the foreign tax might be much
lower than the the Austrian tax that was
charged on the on their subsidiaries. So
you're getting an advantage to them. You
don't have to go that far. What you have
to do is give an imputation credit for
the tax paid abroad which means the
correct amount of credits given. But can
not that pro the problem I'm the
question I'm really searching from is
can an equivalent problem arise at a
domestic level or not? Yes, it can do
can't it? Yes, I mean 89 is drafted on
the assumption that in order to achieve
achieve equivalence
uh you you you have an imputation system
abroad because the foreign company may
have made paid tax at a lower level than
the domestic company paying a dividend
to it. Yes. uh but the assumption must
be that the domestic company paying the
dividend is paying tax at the same rate
as the recipient company and it's that
this is the additional problem which
emerges in FII2. Yes. Yeah. That that's
really the point that I so
well we're being so 89 hasn't hasn't
picked up differential within the
recipient member states country between
the effective tax rate and the and the
nominal tax rate no
[Music]
simple point I think yes
you might be receiving dividends from
companies where there is no tax or tax
is charged at very low rate or or
whatever and um therefore you're giving
giving an advantage to to to people who
establish in those countries over those
who establish in Austria domestic. The
principle it's addressing is the
achievement of the same pack tax burden
or equivalent. Yes. It won't be the
same. It will be equivalent. Yes. Yes.
Exactly. It's all about equivalence and
trying to achieve equivalence. Whatever
that means, but it it doesn't mean
identical. It doesn't mean the same.
That's important because everyone
recognizes you're not in the same
position. If you invest in a foreign
country, you're never going to be in the
same position as you invest in in your
own country because the tax systems are
different just as a matter of tax. All
right. Well, we move on. So, that was
the point that then what they were then
dealing with in 90 was the switch over
that that is in order to qualify for
exemption rather than imputation, you
had to prove a lot of things which it
was being said were impossible or very
difficult to prove. And the court said
that's not a problem. if they even if
they're impossible, you can still apply
the the imputation system. And then they
go on to consider the administrative
burdens. Um
this is um excessive administrative
burdens imposed to qualify for the
amputation method. And again they say
that the fact that compared with an
exemption system, an amputation system
opposes additional burdens is is is um
simply the way things are. It's not a
difference in treatment.
So the the the answer to the question
was that
different different amount different
requirements for information didn't
cause there to be a a problem in EU law.
In this section
um there is a discussion of the
imputation system. Um and paragraph
and 99
deals with that. So 98 says whilst the
company receiving dividends does not
have itself have all the information
relating to the corporation tax that's
been charged on the dividends
distributed by a company established
another member state or a non-member
party. Such information is known in any
event to the latter company.
Accordingly, any difficulty that the
recipient company may have in providing
the information required relating to the
tax paid by the company distributing
dividends is connected not to the
inherent complexity of the information
but to a possible lack of cooperation on
the part of the company that has the
information. As the advocate general
states in point 58, the inadequate flow
of information to the investor is not a
problem for which the member state
concerned should have to answer. So
that's an important principle the
European Court is setting down which is
it's not the problem of the member state
uh that there is practical difficulties
in getting the information.
The information exists it's simply it
may be very difficult to get it but
that's not a problem for the for the
member state. That is simply inherent in
the imputation system. If you grant a
credit for tax paid, it's inherent in
that that the company claiming the
credit has to prove what the tax paid
was.
And it's not good enough for them to
say, "We don't we can't find it out
because they won't tell us."
And that that's essentially what Mr.
Justice Henderson was relying on. you
have seen in his judgment, but he was
dealing with essentially the issues that
are the cross appeal here on issue four.
Um, he was dealing with the argument
that if if it is if it is if they're
required to prove the tax paid,
look, it's it's just not possible to do
that. Um, and his answer relying on this
was, well, that's not a problem for the
member state.
And and then we can see paragraph 99
refers to this simplified procedure.
And this is quite important because a
lot of reliance is placed on the fact
that in in this in Austria there was an
simplified administrative procedure for
determining but importantly it was it
was for determining the actual tax paid
by the company making the distribution.
So they say furthermore as the Austrian
government observes the notice of 13th
June 2008 has simplified the evidence
necessary in order to receive a credit
for the foreign tax in that when
calculating the tax paid abroad. So this
is all part of the process of
calculating the tax paid abroad account
is taken of the following formula. The
profit of the company distributing
dividends must be multiplied by the
nominal rate of corporation tax
applicable in the state in which that
company is established and by the
holding of the recipient company in the
capital of the company distributing
dividends. Such a calculation requires
only limited cooperation on the part of
the company distributing dividends or of
the investment fund when the holding
concern is possessed through such a
fund.
So that's the reference to that and and
there is there is earlier on in the
judgment you can see page MS page 2443
in in the recitation of the facts
paragraph 7
there is a more detailed description of
this procedure
of the of the notice
and it's particularly important to look
At the third bullet point,
this is what you have to provide a meth
a precise indication of the rate of
corporation tax to which the company
making the distribution is subject in
the state in which it is established. If
it is not subject to the normal tax
regime of the state which is established
in that, for example, it's a benefit of
more favorable tax rate, a personal tax
exemption or significant tax exemptions
or reductions, the rate of tax actually
applicable must be given.
So what what's what's clear about this
system even whatever you whatever
significance you think it had was it it
did require
the Austrian company
to provide the information as to the
actual
tax rate that actually is actually
applied to the company
making the distribution the foreign
company.
So what's said in paragraph 99 is is
actually a a simplification of the of
the scheme as described in paragraph 7.
Yes, exactly.
But I thought I it doesn't meet this
point and
well it is still purporting to
in paragraph 99 to be calculating the
tax paid abroad. Yes. Yeah.
So what you've got to show under this
system for instance is that they're
actually paying tax at that rate. In
other words, that their income is not
all exempt for instance or
they're not they've not got some special
tax regime or anything like that. It's
not it's not saying you can simply take
the headline rate of tax in the country
and apply that which is which is the
approach that's been taken in this case.
Um
the second point to make about this
simplification is that it it doesn't
play any part in my submission in the in
the decision of the reasoning of the
court. It it is noted as being something
that is there but but the court doesn't
say in any way
that that the that the legislation in
Austria is only only compatible
um with the treaty because of this
simplification measure.
When we look at 104, this is the the
answer.
The answer to the second question
referred therefore is that article 63
must be interpreted as not precluding
legislation of a member state under
which portfolio dividends which a
resident company receives from other
resident company are exempt from
corporation tax. While portfolio
dividends which a resident company
receives from a company established
another member state are subject to tax.
Provided however that the tax paid in
the state in which the last mentioned
company's resident is credited against
the tax payable in the member state of
the recipient company and the
administrative burdens imposed on the
recipient company in order to qualify
for such a credit are not excessive.
Information demanded by the national tax
authority from the company receiving
dividends that relates to the tax that
has actually been charged on the profits
of the company distributing dividends in
the state in which the latter is
resident is an intrinsic part of the
very operation of the amputation method
and cannot be regarded an excessive
administrative burden.
So we would submit the answer is quite
clear. First of all, it's enough that
you grant credit for tax paid and that
it is perfectly legitimate to ask the
company to prove what that tax was.
Question three concerned the um the
situation in which no tax credit was
given at all in Austria.
uh and and and paragraph 138 the answer
was I think unex not unexpectedly that
article 63 precluded legislation which
exempted portfolio dividends but for
which for dividends by a company
established a non-member state provided
neither exemption nor a system which a
credit is granted
uh for the tax the company paid in the
state in which it was resent. So there
was no credit or no exemption at all.
And and then question four
concerned
the what I would call the conforming
interpretation which was made by the
Austrian courts.
Um
so if you look at the fourth question,
the referring tribunal seeks in essence
to ascertain whether article 63
precludes a national authority from
applying the imputation method in the
case of portfolio dividends from
companies established a non-member state
party to the EA agreement which the
Republic of Austria has not concluded a
comprehensive agreement with regard to
administrative matters despite the fact
that that method results in allegedly
excessive administrative burden for the
recipient of the dividends on the ground
that application of that method
according to the decision of the that
that's the um administrative court in
Austria comes closest to the will of the
legislature when an applicability of the
10th old threshold would give rise to
tax exemption and therefore
automatically prevents economic double
taxation for portfolio dividends from
companies established in non-member
states. So they're asking whether in a
situation in which the court has if you
like um there wasn't this system in the
black letter law but the court has
interpreted the law as providing you
with this credit whether um that is
legitimate despite the fact that there
is an alleged excessive administrative
burden on on those who receive the
dividends in proving what the the
foreign tax was.
Um and
the the answer to that question is the
same as the answer to the previous
questions. Uh they say at paragraph 144,
the allegedly excessive administrative
burden that application of the
imputation method involves has already
been examined in paragraphs 92 to 99 or
104 of the present judgment.
And then the answer to the the fourth
question,
article 63 does not preclude the
practice of a national tax authority
which for dividends from certain
non-member states applies the imputation
method where the holding of the
recipient company and the capital of the
company making the distribution is below
a certain threshold and the exemption
method above that threshold whilst it
systematically applies the exemption
method nationally sourced dividends.
So that that's exactly we would say the
system that that um we are arguing for
provided however that the mechanisms in
question designed to prevent or mitigate
distributed profits being liable to a
series of charges lead to equivalent
results. The fact that the national tax
authority demands information from the
company receiving dividends relating to
the tax that has actually been charged
on the profits of the company
distributing them in the non-member
state in which the latter is written is
an intrinsic part of the very oper
operation of the imputation method and
does not affect as such the equivalence
between the exemption and amputation
method. So that answers the point if if
it was to be made that it's all it's all
very well saying that you can impose um
administrative burdens if the
legislation provides for it but but not
in a situation where it's a conforming
interpretation being adopted by the
court which is what we we have in this
this country this case and the answer to
that is it's exactly the same whether
it's the law as written or it's
conforming interpretation
um the the position on administered
burden It's exactly the same.
It's also important to notice we we say
significant that this case which was
also decided
you'll see Judge Leonards who was the
reporter in this case features heavily
in many of these cases including the
second reference. It's significant to
note despite the fact he was involved in
both this case and the reference in the
present case and FI number two um that
there's no hint in this case which
concerns portfolio dividends with with
the idea that the foreign nominal rate
might be a relevant factor.
We only find that when we come to FI
number two which is the case I was just
going to turn to or would that be a
convenient me? It would not. How how are
you doing in terms of your submissions?
Heaven knows. I I I think I think once
we've cleared the ground with this, we
can we can deal with the submissions
reasonably briefly after that. I I will
have to look at SRA, I'm afraid.
2:00.